Finding aid to the Priscilla Van der Poel Papers CA.MS.00107
Smith College Archives
Priscilla Van der Poel Papers
1926-1994
Smith College Archives
Van der Poel, Priscilla Paine.
CA.MS.00107
3.292 linear feet (5 containers)
The Priscilla Van der Poel Papers contain materials primarily concerned with the professor's teaching career at Smith, but also reveal much about her social life. Material includes correspondence, programs, writings, photographs, diaries, and collected ephemera.
Biographical / Historical
Priscilla Paine was born on April 9, 1907, in Brooklyn, New York, to Frederick H. and Mary (Tillinghast) Paine. She graduated from Smith College in 1928 and went to Europe to continue her artistic development. In Rome she attended the British Academy before returning to New York City to participate in the Art Students League. She also studied interior design at the New York School of Interior Decoration, and completed several decorating jobs in New York and later Northampton (including a few Smith College buildings). Van der Poel wrote in her resume that she left a "salary offer of $3900 in New York for one of $600 here at Smith, because she cared about art, about studying, about teaching, and about Smith College, more than about New York business." She joined the faculty of the Department of Art in 1934. In 1937, she completed a master's degree, also from Smith. It appears Paine married around 1938, when she begins to be listed as Mrs. Van der Poel in the course catalogs, but there does not seem to be any mention of her husband in this collection of papers.
Van der Poel's main professional interests were modern art, design and decoration, and Latin-American art. Early in her teaching career, she was assigned introductory studio art and design courses. Later, in addition to the design courses, she taught modern art and art theory courses. In 1945 she was promoted from assistant to associate professor. Van der Poel also held many administrative positions, but she remained adamant that teaching, not administrative work, was her passion. Besides a prominent role as the Dean of the Class of 1949, she served on the college admission board, the scholarship committee, the Administrative Board, the Conference Committee, the Honors Committee, the Committee in Honorary Degrees, and was chairman of the Lecture Committee from 1950-52. She also served a distinguished term as chairman of the Art Department from 1955 to 1958. She retired in 1972.
Van der Poel traveled abroad frequently throughout her life. She often went to Europe for the summer to conduct special studies and collect photographs and materials for Smith courses. She collected modern art and donated her entire collection to the Smith College Museum of Art before her death. Her active social life revolved around dinner parties that she hosted almost weekly during the latter part of her career. A colleague remembers, "Her elegance was striking, and so were the style and generosity of her hospitality, which was often displayed at gatherings at her apartment." She died on March 19, 1994 at the age of 86.
Scope and Contents
The Priscilla Van der Poel Papers, 1926-1994, contain materials primarily concerned with the professor's teaching career at Smith, but also reveal much about her social life. Types of materials include correspondence, clippings, programs, notes, typescripts, photographs, diaries, and collected ephemera.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series:
I. Biography
II. Professional Activities
III. Correspondence
IV. Travel
V. Writings
VI. Social Activities
VII. Photographs
VII. Oversize Materials
Related Material
See also 52. Art Department Records
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Priscilla Van der Poel Papers were donated by Mrs. Elliott Carlisle in April 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Art--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts --Northampton.; Van der Poel, Priscilla Paine.; Smith College--Faculty.; Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973.; Duckett, Eleanor Shipley.; Mendenhall, Cornelia.; Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin.; Carlisle, Elliott, Mrs.; Carlisle, Elliott, Mrs.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY
  - General, 1994; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 1)
  - Education, Smith Class of 1928, 1926-28; 1953 (Box 1039.1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Artwork, 1944-46; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 3)
  - Career Highlights, 1935-72; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 4)
  - Dean of the Class of 1949, 1945-1949 (Box 1039.1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions and Events, 1948-77 (Box 1039.1, Folder 6)
  - Interior Decoration, 1944; 1949; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 7)
  - Speeches - Clippings, 1947-64; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches - Programs, 1938-56 (Box 1039.1, Folder 9)
  - Teaching - General, 1939-62; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 10)
  - Teaching - General course materials, 1947-51; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 11)
  - Teaching - Lecture Notes, 1944-49; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-68 (Box 1039.1, Folder 13)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - A-B (Box 1039.1, Folder 14)
  - C (Box 1039.1, Folder 15)
  - D (Box 1039.1, Folder 16)
  - E-G (Box 1039.1, Folder 17)
  - H-K (Box 1039.1, Folder 18)
  - L (Box 1039.1, Folder 19)
  - M (Box 1039.1, Folder 20)
  - N-O (Box 1039.1, Folder 21)
  - P-R (Box 1039.1, Folder 22)
  - S (Box 1039.1, Folder 23)
  - T-W (Box 1039.1, Folder 24)
  - Unidentified, 1947-76 (Box 1039.1, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 26)
  - Alumnae Association, 1946-60; undated (Box 1039.1, Folder 27)
  - 69th Birthday - April 9, 1976 (Box 1039.1, Folder 28)
  - Blank Postcards (Box 1039.1, Folder 29)
- SERIES IV. TRAVEL
  - England (Box 1039.2, Folder 1)
  - France (Box 1039.2, Folder 2)
  - Greece and Turkey (Box 1039.2, Folder 3)
  - Italy (Box 1039.2, Folder 4)
  - New York City (Box 1039.2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1039.2, Folder 6)
- SERIES V. WRITINGS
  - Master's Thesis, 1937 (Box 1039.2, Folder 7)
  - Personal Notes, Miscellaneous (Box 1039.2, Folder 8)
  - Reviews, undated (Box 1039.2, Folder 9)
  - Address Book (Box 1039.3)
  - Travel Diary (line-a-day), 1949 (Box 1039.3)
  - Travel Diary (line-a-day), 1952 (Box 1039.3)
  - Travel Diary (line-a-day), 1954 (Box 1039.3)
  - Travel Diary (line-a-day), 1960 (Box 1039.3)
  - Travel Journal, 1955-57 (Box 1039.3)
- SERIES VI. SOCIAL ACTIVITIES
  - Club Membership cards, undated (Box 1039.4, Folder 1)
  - Dinner parties, 1958-62 (Box 1039.4, Folder 2)
  - Dinner parties, 1963-64 (Box 1039.4, Folder 3)
  - Dinner parties, 1965 (Box 1039.4, Folder 4)
  - Dinner parties, 1966 (Box 1039.4, Folder 5)
  - Dinner parties, 1967 (Box 1039.4, Folder 6)
  - Dinner parties, 1968 (Box 1039.4, Folder 7)
  - Dinner parties, 1969-70 (Box 1039.4, Folder 8)
  - Dinner parties, 1971 (Box 1039.4, Folder 9)
  - Dinner parties, 1972-74 (Box 1039.4, Folder 10)
  - Dinner parties, 1975-76; 1979 (Box 1039.4, Folder 11)
  - Dinner parties - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1039.4, Folder 12)
- SERIES VII. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Priscilla Van der Poel (Box 1039.4, Folder 13)
  - General (Box 1039.4, Folder 14)
  - Student Artwork (Box 1039.4, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified (Box 1039.4, Folder 16)
- SERIES VIII. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Artwork (Box 1039.5)